[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "The multiplexer----------- is used to decide which value is transferred to be written back to the register file.",
    "options": ["MP2", "MP3", "MP4", "MP5"],
    "correct": "MP5"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "Which of the following condition is evaluated when executing the branch instruction “brzr R2, R1”?",
    "options": ["If(R2==0)", "If( R1 >0 )", "If( R1==0)", "If( R1 < 0)"],
    "correct": "If( R1==0)"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "In case of SRC processor, bits --------of IR (instruction register) are reserved for the opcode.",
    "options": ["0 to 4", "11 to 15", "27 to 31", "59 to 63"],
    "correct": "27 to 31"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "Which of the given RTL description is used to represent “load instruction register” (ldr) instruction?",
    "options": [
      "(op<4..0>=6): R[ra] rel",
      "(op<4..0>=2): R[ra] M [rel]",
      "(op<4..0>=2): M[disp] R [ra]",
      "(op<4..0>=2): M[rel] R [ra]"
    ],
    "correct": "(op<4..0>=2): R[ra] M [rel]"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "-------------Instruction is used to divide a register value by immediate value in FALCON-E processor.",
    "options": ["div", "idiv", "divi", "divim"],
    "correct": "divi"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "Which field of machine language instruction is the “type of operation” that is to be performed.",
    "options": [
      "Op-code(or the operation code)",
      "CPU register",
      "Memory Cells",
      "I/O Location"
    ],
    "correct": "Op-code(or the operation code)"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Which of the following control signal is NOT activated during instruction fetch operation?",
    "options": ["PCout", "LC", "LMAR", "Cout"],
    "correct": "Cout"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "In case of FALCON-A------------ instruction are present which are not present in SRC processor.",
    "options": [
      "create and destroy",
      "in and out",
      "open and close",
      "read and write"
    ],
    "correct": "in and out"
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "--------------- provides a temporary storage for the address of memory location to be accessed.",
    "options": ["MAR", "MBR", "PC", "LPC"],
    "correct": "MAR"
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "Which of the following register is used to enable the tri-stable buffers with the MBR?",
    "options": ["MBRout", "MARout", "LMBR", "INC4"],
    "correct": "MBRout"
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "What functionality is performed by the instruction “str R8, 34” of SRC?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R8 with the contents of the memory location M[PC+34]",
      "It will load the register R8 with the contents of the memory location M[34]",
      "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M[PC+34]",
      "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M[34]"
    ],
    "correct": "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M[PC+34]"
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "Program Counter(PC) holds the memory address of:",
    "options": [
      "Previous Instruction",
      "Current Instruction",
      "Next Instruction",
      "Previous and Current Instruction"
    ],
    "correct": "Next Instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "What is the working of Processor Status Word (PSW)?",
    "options": [
      "To hold the current status of the processor",
      "To hold the current address of the process",
      "To hold the instruction that the computer is currently processing",
      "To hold the address of the next instruction in memory that is to be executed"
    ],
    "correct": "To hold the current status of the processor"
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "mul is the example of a(n) ------------operation.",
    "options": ["Logic", "Shift", "Arithmetic", "Data transfer"],
    "correct": "Arithmetic"
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "Control Signal for RTL “IR< ---MBR” will be---------",
    "options": ["MBRout,LIR", "PC< --C", "PC< --MBR", "PC< --IR"],
    "correct": "MBRout,LIR"
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "What does the instruction”ldr R3, 58” of SRC do?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M[PC+58]",
      "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself(PC+58)",
      "It will store register R3 contents to the memory location M[PC+58]",
      "It will store the value of register R3 at the relative address itself(PC+58)"
    ],
    "correct": "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M[PC+58]"
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "The status register of the 68000 has---------condition codes.",
    "options": ["2", "3", "5", "8"],
    "correct": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "Which of the instruction is used to load register from memory using relative address?",
    "options": [
      "ld instruction",
      "ldr instruction",
      "lar instruction",
      "str instruction"
    ],
    "correct": "ldr instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "For the ------ type instruction, we require a register to hold the data that is to be loaded from the memory, or stored back to the memory.",
    "options": ["Jump", "Control", "L", "load/store", "Branch"],
    "correct": "load/store"
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "In a processor,------------is responsible for the synchronization of internal as well external events.",
    "options": [
      "Memory Unit",
      "Data Unit",
      "Arithmetic & Logic Unit",
      "Control Unit"
    ],
    "correct": "Control Unit"
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "In CPU design, -------------creates or forms the interface between the data path and control unit.",
    "options": ["Buses", "ALU", "Control signal", "cache"],
    "correct": "Control signal"
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "------------- Control signal enables the input to the PC for receiving a value that is currently on the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["LPC", "INC4", "LC", "Cout"],
    "correct": "LPC"
  },
  {
    "id": "23",
    "question": "In SRC, the effective address is computed a run-time by adding a constant to value of --------- register.",
    "options": ["FLAGS", "IR", "PC", "Ra"],
    "correct": "PC"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "----------- control signal allow the content of the program counter register to be written onto the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["INC4", "LPC", "PCout", "LC"],
    "correct": "PCout"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "In ----------instruction format of EAGLE processor, there is no field reserved for the operands.",
    "options": ["Type V", "Type Y", "Type X", "Type Z"],
    "correct": "Type Z"
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "In Type C instruction of SRC,----------- bits are allocated for constant values.",
    "options": ["16", "17", "21", "22"],
    "correct": "22"
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "A general purpose digital computer has----------main components.",
    "options": ["2", "3", "4", "5"],
    "correct": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "The instruction ---------- will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M[PC+56].",
    "options": ["lar R3,M[56]", "ldr R3,M[56]", "ldr R3,56", "lr R3,[56]"],
    "correct": "ldr R3,56"
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "In FALCON-A instruction format of Type-2 constants and variable should be in the range of.",
    "options": [
      "-132 to +131",
      "-164 to + 163",
      "-32 to + 31",
      "-128 to + 127"
    ],
    "correct": "-32 to + 31"
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "In a FALCON-A assembly program, labels are used to implement----------- jump.",
    "options": ["Direct", "Indirect", "Relative", "Displacement"],
    "correct": "Relative"
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "In “Jump [8]” instruction, the size of the constant fields is---------bits.",
    "options": ["4", "5", "8", "16"],
    "correct": "8"
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "The multiplexer --------- is used to decide which value is transferred to be written back to the register file.",
    "options": ["MP2", "MP3", "MP3", "MP5"],
    "correct": "MP5"
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "-------------- is a register which takes input from the ALSU as memory address to be accessed and transfer the memory contents on that location onto the memory sub-system.",
    "options": ["PC", "MBR", "MAR", "IR"],
    "correct": "MAR"
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "In pipe-lined processor, there should be a ---------port register file so that if the register write and register read stages overlap they can be performed in parallel.",
    "options": ["Four", "Three", "Two", "One"],
    "correct": "Two"
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "question": "Which of the following registers is used as an implicit operand in MUL/DIV instruction of FALCON-A?",
    "options": ["R0", "PC", "IR", "SP"],
    "correct": "R0"
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "question": "Which one of the following control signals causes the data from the bus to be read into the register MAR.",
    "options": ["MARout", "MARin", "LMAR", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "LMAR"
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "question": "To set the value of micro-PC from branch address, the value of 4 to 1 multiplexer is------------",
    "options": ["00", "01", "10", "11"],
    "correct": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "question": "The instruction “PUSH A” is an example of ------------",
    "options": [
      "0-address instruction",
      "1-address instruction",
      "2-address instruction",
      "3-address instruction"
    ],
    "correct": "1-address instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "question": "Which of the following branch instruction has a condition which is always executed?",
    "options": ["JZ", "JUMP", "JPL", "JMI"],
    "correct": "JUMP"
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "question": "--------------hazard occurs when attempting to access same resource in different ways at the same time.",
    "options": ["Branch", "Data", "Structural", "Instruction"],
    "correct": "Structural"
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "question": "--------------- is an example of Miscellaneous instruction.",
    "options": ["Shift", "Store", "Halt", "Call"],
    "correct": "Halt"
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "question": "Which type of instructions enables mathematical computations?",
    "options": ["Arithmetic", "Control", "Data transfer", "Numeric"],
    "correct": "Arithmetic"
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "question": "VLIW Stands for-------------",
    "options": [
      "Variable Length Instruction Word",
      "Very Long Instruction Word",
      "Very Long Instruction Width",
      "Variable Length Instruction Width"
    ],
    "correct": "Very Long Instruction Word"
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT related to the architecture of the computer?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction set",
      "Control signal",
      "I/O mechanism",
      "Memory addressing modules"
    ],
    "correct": "Control signal"
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "question": "In SRC, the general-purpose register file includes--------------registers, each 32 bit wide.",
    "options": [
      "6 Registers R0 to R15",
      "24 Registers R0 to R23",
      "32 Registers R0 to R31",
      "64 Registers R0 to R63"
    ],
    "correct": "32 Registers R0 to R31"
  },
  {
    "id": 46,
    "question": "Which of the following RTL description is used for specifying the operation of an SRC instruction?",
    "options": ["IR<31..27>", "IR<22..26>", "IR<21..17>", "IR<21..0>"],
    "correct": "IR<31..27>"
  },
  {
    "id": 47,
    "question": "What is the size of the memory space that is available to FALCON-A processor?",
    "options": ["2^8 bytes", "2^16 bytes", "2^32 bytes", "2^64 bytes"],
    "correct": "2^16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 48,
    "question": "How can we refer to an instruction register (IR), of 16 bits (numbered 0 to 15) using RTL.",
    "options": ["IR<16..0>", "IR<15..0>", "IR<16..1>", "IR<15..1>"],
    "correct": "IR<15..0>"
  },
  {
    "id": 49,
    "question": "What is the working of Processor Status Word (PSW)",
    "options": [
      "To hold the current status of the processor.",
      "To hold the address of the current process",
      "To hold the instruction that the computer is currently processing",
      "To hold the address of the next instruction in memory that is to be executed"
    ],
    "correct": "To hold the current status of the processor."
  },
  {
    "id": 50,
    "question": "What does the instruction “ldr R3, 58” of SRC do?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+58]",
      "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+58).",
      "It will store the register R3 contents to the memory location M [PC+58]",
      "No operation"
    ],
    "correct": "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+58]"
  },
  {
    "id": 51,
    "question": "What is the instruction length of the FALCON-E processor?",
    "options": ["8 bits", "16 bits", "32 bits", "64 bits"],
    "correct": "32 bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 52,
    "question": "Which one of the following portions of an instruction represents the operation to be performed?",
    "options": ["Address", "Instruction code", "Opcode", "Operand"],
    "correct": "Opcode"
  },
  {
    "id": 53,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the highest level of abstraction in digital design in which the computer architect views the system for the description of system components and their interconnections?",
    "options": [
      "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)",
      "Instruction Set Level",
      "Register Transfer Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)"
  },
  {
    "id": 54,
    "question": "Identify the opcode, destination register (DR), source registers (SA and SB i/e source register A and source register B) from the following example. ADD R1, R2, R3",
    "options": [
      "Opcode= R1, DR=ADD, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= R2, DR=ADD, SA=R1, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R3, SA=R2, SB=R1"
    ],
    "correct": "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3"
  },
  {
    "id": 55,
    "question": "Which one of the following circuit design levels is called the gate level?",
    "options": [
      "Logic Design Level",
      "Circuit Level",
      "Mask Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Logic Design Level"
  },
  {
    "id": 56,
    "question": "The CPU includes three types of instructions, which have different operands and will need different representations. Which one of the instructions requires two source registers?",
    "options": [
      "Jump and branch format instructions",
      "Immediate format instructions",
      "Register format instructions",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "correct": "Register format instructions"
  },
  {
    "id": 57,
    "question": "P: R3 <- R5 MAR <- IR These two are instructions written using RTL .If these two operations is to occur simultaneously then which symbol will we use to separate them so that it becomes a correct statement with the condition that two operations occur simultaneously?",
    "options": ["Parentheses ()", "Arrow <-", "Colon :", "Comma ,"],
    "correct": "Comma ,"
  },
  {
    "id": 58,
    "question": "In which of the following instructions the data move between a register in the processor and a memory location (or another register) and are also called data movement?",
    "options": [
      "Arithmetic/logic",
      "Load/store",
      "Test/branch",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Load/store"
  },
  {
    "id": 59,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the highest level of abstraction in digital design in which the computer architect views the system for the description of system components and their interconnections?",
    "options": [
      "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)",
      "Instruction Set Level",
      "Register Transfer Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)"
  },
  {
    "id": 60,
    "question": "Identify the opcode, destination register (DR), source registers (SA and SB i/e source register A and source register B) from the following example. ADD R1, R2, R3",
    "options": [
      "Opcode= R1, DR=ADD, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= R2, DR=ADD, SA=R1, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R3, SA=R2, SB=R1"
    ],
    "correct": "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3"
  },
  {
    "id": 61,
    "question": "Which one of the following circuit design levels is called the gate level?",
    "options": [
      "Logic Design Level",
      "Circuit Level",
      "Mask Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Logic Design Level"
  },
  {
    "id": 62,
    "question": "The CPU includes three types of instructions, which have different operands and will need different representations. Which one of the instructions requires two source registers?",
    "options": [
      "Jump and branch format instructions",
      "Immediate format instructions",
      "Register format instructions",
      "All of the above"
    ],
    "correct": "Register format instructions"
  },
  {
    "id": 63,
    "question": "P: R3 <- R5 MAR <- IR These two are instructions written using RTL .If these two operations is to occur simultaneously then which symbol will we use to separate them so that it becomes a correct statement with the condition that two operations occur simultaneously?",
    "options": ["Parentheses ()", "Arrow <-", "Colon :", "Comma ,"],
    "correct": "Comma ,"
  },
  {
    "id": 64,
    "question": "In which of the following instructions the data move between a register in the processor and a memory location (or another register) and are also called data movement?",
    "options": [
      "Arithmetic/logic",
      "Load/store",
      "Test/branch",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Load/store"
  },
  {
    "id": 65,
    "question": "What does the word ‘D’ in the ‘D-flip-Flop’ stands for?",
    "options": ["Data", "Digital", "Dynamic", "Double"],
    "correct": "Data"
  },
  {
    "id": 66,
    "question": "The instruction--------------- will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+56]",
    "options": ["Add R3, 56", "lar R3, 56", "ldr R3, 56", "str R3, 56"],
    "correct": "ldr R3, 56"
  },
  {
    "id": 67,
    "question": "What is the instruction length of the FALCON-E processor?",
    "options": ["8 bits", "16 bits", "32 bits"],
    "correct": "32 bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 68,
    "question": "Which one of the following are the code size and the Number of memory bytes respectively for a 2-address instruction?",
    "options": [
      "4 bytes, 7 bytes",
      "7 bytes, 16 bytes",
      "10 bytes, 19 bytes",
      "13 bytes, 22 bytes"
    ],
    "correct": "7 bytes, 16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 69,
    "question": "Which one of the following portions of an instruction represents the operation to be performed?",
    "options": ["Address", "Instruction code", "Opcode", "Operand"],
    "correct": "Opcode"
  },
  {
    "id": 70,
    "question": "Which operator is used to ‘name’ registers, or part of registers, in the Register Transfer Language?",
    "options": [":=", "&", "%", "©"],
    "correct": ":="
  },
  {
    "id": 71,
    "question": "What is the size of the memory space that is available to FALCON-A processor?",
    "options": ["2^8 bytes", "2^16 bytes", "2^32 bytes", "2^64 bytes"],
    "correct": "2^16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 72,
    "question": "An “assembler” that runs on one processor and translates an assembly language program written for another processor into the machine language of the other processor is called a ----------------",
    "options": ["compiler", "cross assembler", "debugger", "linker"],
    "correct": "cross assembler"
  },
  {
    "id": 73,
    "question": "Which instruction is used to store register to memory using relative address.",
    "options": [
      "ld instruction",
      "ldr instruction",
      "lar instruction",
      "str instruction"
    ],
    "correct": "str instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 74,
    "question": "Which of the following can be defined as an address of the operand in a computer type instruction or the target address in a branch type instruction?",
    "options": [
      "Base address",
      "Binary address",
      "Effective address",
      "All of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Effective address"
  },
  {
    "id": 75,
    "question": "How can we refer to an instruction register (IR), of 16 bits (numbered 0 to 15) using RTL?",
    "options": ["IR<16..0>", "IR<15..0>", "IR<16..1>", "IR<15..1>"],
    "correct": "IR<15..0>"
  },
  {
    "id": 76,
    "question": "What functionality is performed by the instruction “str R8, 34” of SRC?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R8 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+34]",
      "It will load the register R8 with the relative address itself (PC+34).",
      "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M [PC+34]",
      "No operation"
    ],
    "correct": "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M [PC+34]"
  },
  {
    "id": 77,
    "question": "Which type of instructions help in changing the flow of the program as and when required?",
    "options": ["Arithmetic", "Control", "Data transfer", "Floating point"],
    "correct": "Control"
  },
  {
    "id": 78,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are true about RISC processors’ claimed advantages over CISC processors? (a) Keeping regularly accessed variables in registers as opposed to keeping them in memory facilitates faster execution. (b) RISC CPUs outperform CISC CPU’s in procedural programming environments. (c) Instruction pipelining has helped RISC CPU’s to attain a target of 1 cycle per instruction. (d) It is easier to maintain the “family concept” in RISC CPU.",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b) &(c)",
      "(b), (c) & (e)",
      "(c), (d) & (e)",
      "(a), (c) & (d)"
    ],
    "correct": "(a), (c) & (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": 79,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the highest level of abstraction in digital design in which the computer architect views the system for the description of system components and their interconnections?",
    "options": [
      "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)",
      "Instruction Set Level",
      "Register Transfer Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)"
  },
  {
    "id": 80,
    "question": "Which one of the following is/are the features of Register Transfer Language? a) It is a symbolic language b) It is describing the internal organization of digital computers c) It is an elementary operation performed (during one clock pulse), on the information stored in one or more registers d) It is high level language.",
    "options": ["(b) only", "& (b) only", ",(b) & (d)", "(b),(c) & (d)"],
    "correct": "(b),(c) & (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": 81,
    "question": "Motorola MC68000 is an example of---------microprocessor.",
    "options": ["CISC", "RISC", "SRC", "FALCON"],
    "correct": "CISC"
  },
  {
    "id": 82,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers holds the instruction that is being executed?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Instruction Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 83,
    "question": "For any of the instructions that are a part of the instruction set of the SRC, there are certain required; which may be used to select the appropriate function for the ALU to be performed, to select the appropriate registers, or the appropriate memory location.",
    "options": ["Registers", "Control signals", "Memory", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "Control signals"
  },
  {
    "id": 84,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a data bus.",
    "options": ["8-bit", "16-bit", "24-bit", "32-bit"],
    "correct": "16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 85,
    "question": "In which one of the following techniques, the time a processor spends waiting for instructions to be fetched from memory is minimize",
    "options": ["Perfecting", "Pipelining", "Superscalar operation", "Speedup"],
    "correct": "Pipelining"
  },
  {
    "id": 86,
    "question": "enable the input to the PC for receiving a value that is currently on the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["LPC", "INC4", "LC", "Cout"],
    "correct": "LPC"
  },
  {
    "id": 87,
    "question": "The processor must have a way of saving information about its state or context so that it can be restored upon return from the -------------",
    "options": ["Exception", "Function", "Thread", "Stack"],
    "correct": "Exception"
  },
  {
    "id": 88,
    "question": "-------------is the ability of application software to operate on models of equipment newer than the model for which it was originally developed.",
    "options": [
      "Backward compatibility",
      "Data migration",
      "Reverse engineering",
      "Upward compatibility"
    ],
    "correct": "Upward compatibility"
  },
  {
    "id": 89,
    "question": "control signal allows the contents of the Program Counter register to be written onto the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["INC4", "LPC", "PCout", "LC"],
    "correct": "PCout"
  },
  {
    "id": 90,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers stores a previously calculated value or a value loaded from the main memory?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Accumulator"
  },
  {
    "id": 91,
    "question": "Computer system performance is usually measured by the ---------------",
    "options": [
      "Time to execute a program or program mix",
      "The speed with which it executes programs",
      "Processor’s utilization in solving the problems",
      "Instructions that can be carried out simultaneously"
    ],
    "correct": "Time to execute a program or program mix"
  },
  {
    "id": 92,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a address bus.",
    "options": ["8-bit", "16-bit", "24-bit", "32-bit"],
    "correct": "16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 93,
    "question": "Which one of the following register(s) that is/are programmer invisible and is/are required to hold an operand or result value while the bus is busy transmitting some other value?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction Register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory Buffer Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 94,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a address bus and a data bus.",
    "options": [
      "8-bit , 8-bit",
      "16-bit , 16-bit",
      "16-bit , 24-bit",
      "16-bit , 32-bit"
    ],
    "correct": "16-bit , 16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 95,
    "question": "------------is the ability of application software to operate on models of equipment newer than the model for which it was originally developed.",
    "options": [
      "Backward compatibility",
      "Data migration",
      "Reverse engineering",
      "Upward compatibility"
    ],
    "correct": "Upward compatibility"
  },
  {
    "id": 96,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers stores a previously calculated value or a value loaded from the main memory?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Accumulator"
  },
  {
    "id": 97,
    "question": "Which one of the following register(s) contain(s) the address of the place the CPU wants to work with in the main memory and is/are directly connected to the RAM chips on the motherboard?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction Register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory address register"
  },
  {
    "id": 98,
    "question": "FALCON-A processor bus has 16 lines or is 16-bits wide while that of SRC is wide.",
    "options": ["8-bits", "16-bits", "32-bits", "64-bits"],
    "correct": "32-bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 99,
    "question": "enable the input to the PC for receiving a value that is currently on the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["LPC", "INC4", "LC", "Cout"],
    "correct": "LPC"
  },
  {
    "id": 100,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a data bus.",
    "options": ["8-bit", "16-bit", "24-bit", "32-bit"],
    "correct": "16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 101,
    "question": "For any of the instructions that are a part of the instruction set of the SRC, there are certain required; which may be used to select the appropriate function for the ALU to be performed, to select appropriate registers, or the appropriate memory location",
    "options": ["Registers", "Control signals", "Memory", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "Control signals"
  },
  {
    "id": 102,
    "question": "Among the two approaches available to design a control unit, hardware approach is relatively---------- as compared to micro-programming.",
    "options": ["Slow", "Fast", "Average", "Better"],
    "correct": "Fast"
  },
  {
    "id": 103,
    "question": "The MAR is connected directly to the-----------",
    "options": ["MBR", "CPU Internal bus", "CPU external bus", "LIC"],
    "correct": "CPU external bus"
  },
  {
    "id": 104,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a part of processor state?",
    "options": ["IR", "PC", "Stacks", "Registers"],
    "correct": "Stacks"
  },
  {
    "id": 105,
    "question": "--------------------- form the branch control field in the micro instruction.",
    "options": ["C Bits", "M Bits", "B BITS", "M Bits"],
    "correct": "B BITS"
  },
  {
    "id": 106,
    "question": "During the RESET operation of processor, control step counter is set to---------------",
    "options": ["1", "0", "2", "-1"],
    "correct": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": 107,
    "question": "An “assembler” that runs on one processor and translates an assembly language program written for another processor into the machine language of the other processor is called a------------",
    "options": ["Compiler", "Cross assembler", "Debugger", "linker"],
    "correct": "Cross assembler"
  },
  {
    "id": 108,
    "question": "In FALCON-A processor, the size of each I/O port is---------------",
    "options": ["16 bits", "8 bits", "8 bytes", "256 bytes"],
    "correct": "16 bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 109,
    "question": "-------------------is defined as the number of instructions processed per second.",
    "options": ["Memory access", "Throughput", "ALU operation", "Latency"],
    "correct": "Throughput"
  },
  {
    "id": 110,
    "question": "In FALCON-A ISA, which of the following opcodes is used to perform “No Operation”?",
    "options": ["20", "21", "22", "23"],
    "correct": "20"
  },
  {
    "id": 111,
    "question": "-------------------- is an example of Miscellaneous instruction:",
    "options": ["Shift", "Store", "Halt", "Cell"],
    "correct": "Halt"
  },
  {
    "id": 112,
    "question": "To apply two shifts to an input number using the barrel shifter, the control signals S1 and S0 of the shifter should be .",
    "options": [
      "S1 = 1 and S0 = 1",
      "S1 = 0 and S0 = 1",
      "S1 = 1 and S0 = 0",
      "S1 = 2 and S0 = 0"
    ],
    "correct": "S1 = 1 and S0 = 1"
  },
  {
    "id": 113,
    "question": "Which one of the followings is the correct RTL description for sign extensions of an 8-bit constant:",
    "options": [
      "(8aIR<7>©IR<7..0>)",
      "(8aIR<5>©IR<8..0>",
      "(8aIR<7>©IR<6..0>",
      "(8aIR<8>©IR<7..0>"
    ],
    "correct": "(8aIR<7>©IR<7..0>)"
  },
  {
    "id": 114,
    "question": "In MC68000,--------------- register is used as stack pointer:",
    "options": ["A0", "A7", "D0", "D7"],
    "correct": "A7"
  },
  {
    "id": 115,
    "question": "In which of the following instructions, the data moves between a register in the processor and a memory location:",
    "options": ["Arithmetic", "Load/ Store", "Branch", "Logic"],
    "correct": "Load/ Store"
  },
  {
    "id": 116,
    "question": "The size of data bus of mc68000 processor is:",
    "options": ["8 bits", "16 bits", "20 bits", "32 bits"],
    "correct": "16 bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 117,
    "question": "Which one of the following operations is NOT performed by using miscellaneous instructions?",
    "options": [
      "Clearing all registers",
      "Stopping the processor",
      "NOP",
      "Returning from a procedure"
    ],
    "correct": "Clearing all registers"
  },
  {
    "id": 118,
    "question": "In case of FALCON-A--------------- instructions are present which are not present in the SRC processor:",
    "options": [
      "Create and destroy",
      "In and out",
      "Open and close",
      "Read and write"
    ],
    "correct": "In and out"
  },
  {
    "id": 119,
    "question": "In Type C instruction of SRC , -------------------- bits are allocated for content value:",
    "options": ["16", "17", "21", "22"],
    "correct": "22"
  },
  {
    "id": 120,
    "question": "RISC stands for?",
    "options": [
      "Registers internal system cache",
      "Reduced instruction set computer",
      "Registers instruction set computer",
      "Reduced internal system computers"
    ],
    "correct": "Reduced instruction set computer"
  },
  {
    "id": 121,
    "question": "Which of the followings is not an example of super-scalar processors?",
    "options": ["PowerPC601", "IAPX88", "Intel P6", "DEC Alpha 21164"],
    "correct": "IAPX88"
  },
  {
    "id": 122,
    "question": "In EAGLE processor, which of the following notations is used to represent a memory word stored at address 8?",
    "options": [
      "M [8] <0..15>:= M[8]©M[9]",
      "M[8]<15..0>:=M[9] ©M[8]",
      "M[8]<15..0:=M[8] ©M[9]",
      "M[8]<0..15>:=M[9] ©M[8]"
    ],
    "correct": "M[8]<15..0:=M[8] ©M[9]"
  },
  {
    "id": 123,
    "question": "------------------form the branch address field in the micro instruction:",
    "options": ["C bits", "M bits", "B bits", "A bits"],
    "correct": "M bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 124,
    "question": "What does the instruction “idr R3, 58” of SRC do?",
    "options": [
      "It will load register R3 with the contents of the memory location M[PC+58]",
      "It will load register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+58)",
      "It will store register R3 contents to the memory location M[PC+58]",
      "It will store the value of register R3 at the relative address itself (PC+58)"
    ],
    "correct": "It will load register R3 with the contents of the memory location M[PC+58]"
  },
  {
    "id": 125,
    "question": "The SPARC architecture defines a-----------------------that allows for multiple address spaces.",
    "options": [
      "Memory Location Unit(MLU)",
      "Memory Mapping Unit( MMU)",
      "Memory Shifting Unit (MSU)",
      "Memory Arithmetic Unit (MAU)"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory Mapping Unit( MMU)"
  },
  {
    "id": 126,
    "question": "For a processor having 32 general purpose register,--------------- bits are required for each register field in the instruction:",
    "options": ["32", "3", "8", "5"],
    "correct": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": 127,
    "question": "Which of the following registers is/are programmer invisible and is/are required to hold an operand or result value while the bus is busy transmitting some other value?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory Buffer Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 128,
    "question": "In SRC which of the following is a notation which is used to repeat 32- bit memory word stored at address starting from 56?",
    "options": [
      "M[56]<31..0>:=M[56]M[57]M[58]M[59]",
      "M[56]<0..31>:=M[56]M[57]M[58]M[59]",
      "M[56]<0..31>:=M[59]M[58]M[57]M[56]",
      "M[56]<0..31>:=M[59]M[58]M[57]M[56]"
    ],
    "correct": "M[56]<0..31>:=M[59]M[58]M[57]M[56]"
  },
  {
    "id": 129,
    "question": "Which of the following branch instruction has a condition which is always executed?",
    "options": ["JZ", "JUMP", "JPL", "JMI"],
    "correct": "JUMP"
  },
  {
    "id": 130,
    "question": "Which of the following EAGLE instruction is used to initialize all the registers by setting them to 0?",
    "options": ["NOP", "HALT", "INIT", "RESET"],
    "correct": "INIT"
  },
  {
    "id": 131,
    "question": "Which notation do we use to name different fields of a register in RTL?",
    "options": ["0", "<=", "+", ":="],
    "correct": ":="
  },
  {
    "id": 132,
    "question": "Which of the following instruction is considered most important in pipelined EAGLE architecture?",
    "options": ["HALT", "NOP", "INIT", "RESET"],
    "correct": "NOP"
  },
  {
    "id": 133,
    "question": "The ALSU function “INC2” increments the------------- by 2 and the output is stored in the buffer register.",
    "options": ["PC,A", "IR,A", "PC,C", "IR,C"],
    "correct": "PC,C"
  },
  {
    "id": 134,
    "question": "Which temporary register is loaded with either a register value from the register file or a constant from the instruction?",
    "options": ["Y3", "X3", "Z4", "Z5"],
    "correct": "X3"
  },
  {
    "id": 135,
    "question": "“Finite-state machine” concepts are usually used to represent the control unit where every state corresponds to ------------ clock cycles(s).",
    "options": ["1", "2", "4", "16"],
    "correct": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": 136,
    "question": "Total number of data registers in Motorola 68000 processor are----------",
    "options": ["8", "12", "24", "32"],
    "correct": "8"
  },
  {
    "id": 137,
    "question": "-----------------instruction is used to load a register with an immediate value.",
    "options": ["la", "lar", "ld", "ldr"],
    "correct": "la"
  },
  {
    "id": 138,
    "question": "A computer belongs to which of the following subset of the systems?",
    "options": [
      "Mechanical system",
      "Electrical system",
      "Optical system",
      "Magnetic system"
    ],
    "correct": "Electrical system"
  },
  {
    "id": 139,
    "question": "In FALCON-A processor , the size of each I/O port is-------------",
    "options": ["16 bit", "8 bit", "8 bytes", "256 bytes"],
    "correct": "16 bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 140,
    "question": "Type A of SRC has which of the following instruction?",
    "options": ["(a)&(b)", "(b)&(c)", "(a)&(e)", "(b)&(e)"],
    "correct": "(a)&(e)"
  },
  {
    "id": 141,
    "question": "In which of the following technique, the time a processor spends waiting for instruction to be fetched from memory is minimized?",
    "options": [
      "Perfecting",
      "Pipelining",
      "Super-scalar operation",
      "Speed up"
    ],
    "correct": "Pipelining"
  },
  {
    "id": 142,
    "question": "------------------ is the ability of application software to operate on models of equipment near than the model for which it originally developed.",
    "options": [
      "Backward compatibility",
      "Data migration",
      "Reverse engineering",
      "Upward compatibility"
    ],
    "correct": "Upward compatibility"
  },
  {
    "id": 143,
    "question": "Which of the following register stores a previously calculated value or a value loaded from the main memory?",
    "options": ["Accumulator", "Address Mask", "Program counter"],
    "correct": "Accumulator"
  },
  {
    "id": 144,
    "question": "Computer system performance is usually measured by the ----------",
    "options": [
      "Time to execute a program or program mix",
      "The speed in which it executes programs",
      "Processor’s utilization in solving the problems",
      "Instructions that can be carried out simultaneously"
    ],
    "correct": "Time to execute a program or program mix"
  },
  {
    "id": 145,
    "question": "Which of the following code size and the number of memory bytes respectively for a 2-address instruction.",
    "options": [
      "4 bytes, 7 bytes",
      "7 bytes ,16 bytes",
      "10 bytes , 19 bytes",
      "13 bytes, 19 bytes"
    ],
    "correct": "7 bytes ,16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 146,
    "question": "Which of the the given below measures is/are used for comparison of performance of various machine?",
    "options": ["Execution time", "MFLOPS", "MIPS", "All of the given"],
    "correct": "All of the given"
  },
  {
    "id": 147,
    "question": "There are------------- type of RESET operation in SRC.",
    "options": ["Three", "Four", "Two", "five"],
    "correct": "Two"
  },
  {
    "id": 148,
    "question": "Type checking allows the--------------to determine memory for variables.",
    "options": ["Compiler", "Debugger", "Linker", "loader"],
    "correct": "Compiler"
  },
  {
    "id": 149,
    "question": "In FALCON-A processor, memory word size is----------------",
    "options": ["1 byte", "4 bytes", "8 bytes", "2 bytes"],
    "correct": "2 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 150,
    "question": "What functionality is performed by the by the instruction “lar R3, 36” performed.",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R3 with the contents of memory location M[PC+36]",
      "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+36)",
      "It will store the register R3 contents of memory location M[PC+36]",
      "It will left rotate the value of R3 36 times and will store the value in R3"
    ],
    "correct": "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+36)"
  },
  {
    "id": 151,
    "question": "To connect together five (5) m-bit registers in a point-to-point scheme, connections are required.",
    "options": ["25", "30", "20", "24"],
    "correct": "20"
  },
  {
    "id": 152,
    "question": "For the type instructions, we require a register to hold the data that is to be loaded from the memory, or stored back to the memory.",
    "options": ["JUMP", "LOAD/Store", "Control", "None of the Given"],
    "correct": "LOAD/Store"
  },
  {
    "id": 153,
    "question": "Almost every commercial computer has its own particular language.",
    "options": [
      "3 GL",
      "English Language",
      "High Level Language",
      "Asseembly Language"
    ],
    "correct": "Asseembly Language"
  },
  {
    "id": 154,
    "question": "In a register-based machine having 64 registers, a field is required in instruction to identify a register.",
    "options": ["4-bit", "6-bit", "8-bit", "16-bit"],
    "correct": "6-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "For any of the instructions that are a part of the instruction set of the SRC, there are cerain_________required; which may be used to select the appropriate function for the ALU to be performed, to select the appropriate registers, or the appropriate memory location.",
    "options": ["Register", "Control signals", "Memory", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "Control signals"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "FALCON-A processor bus has 16 lines or is 16-bits wide while that of SRC _____wide.",
    "options": ["8-bits", "16-bits", "32-bits", "64-bits"],
    "correct": "32-bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "What is the instruction length of the FALCON-A processor?",
    "options": ["8-bits", "16-bits", "32-bits", "64-bits"],
    "correct": "16-bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "_________control signals enable the input to the PC for receiving a value that is currently on the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["LPC", "INC4", "LC", "I2"],
    "correct": "LPC"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "Which one of the following is a bi-stable device, capable of storing one bit of information?",
    "options": ["Decoder", "Flip-Flop", "Multiplexer", "Diplexer"],
    "correct": "Flip-Flop"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "Which instruction is used to store register to memory using relative address?",
    "options": [
      "ld instruction",
      "ldr instruction",
      "lar instruction",
      "str instruction"
    ],
    "correct": "str instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Which field of the machine language instruction is the “type of operation” that is to be performed?",
    "options": ["Op-code", "CPU registers", "Momory cells", "I/O locations"],
    "correct": "Op-code"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "The instruction ___________ will load the register R3 with the contenets of the m\\emory location M [PC+56]",
    "options": ["Add R3, 56", "lar R3, 56", "ldr R3, 56", "str R3, 56"],
    "correct": "ldr R3, 56"
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "_______ operation is required to change the processor’s state to a known, defined value.",
    "options": ["Change", "Reset", "Update", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "Reset"
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "which type of instructions help in changing the flow of the program as and when required?",
    "options": ["Arithmetic", "Control", "Data transfer", "Floating point"],
    "correct": "Control"
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers holds the address of the next instruction to be executed?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Program Counter"
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the memory organization of EAGLE processor?",
    "options": ["8-bits", "16-bits", "32-bit", "64-bits"],
    "correct": "16-bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a ______address bus and ______a data bus.",
    "options": [
      "8-bit. 8-bit",
      "16-bit. 16-bit",
      "16-bit. 24-bit",
      "16-bit. 32-bit"
    ],
    "correct": "16-bit. 16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "Type A of SRC has which of the following instructions? A) andi, instruction b) No operation or nop instruction c) lar instruction d) ldr instruction e) Stop operation or stop instruction",
    "options": ["& (b)", "(b) & (c)", "& (e)", "(b) & (e)"],
    "correct": "c) lar instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "What is the instruction length of the SRC processor?",
    "options": ["8 bits", "16 bits", "32 bits", "64 bits"],
    "correct": "32 bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the memory organization of FALCON-E processor?",
    "options": [
      "2^8 * 8 bits",
      "2^16 * 8 bits",
      "2^32 * 8 bits",
      "2^64 * 8 bits"
    ],
    "correct": "2^32 * 8 bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "“If P = 1, then load the contents of register R1 into register R2”. This statement can be written in RTL as:",
    "options": [
      "R1 ¬ R2",
      "P: R1 ¬ R2",
      "P: R2 ¬ R1 (not confirms)",
      "P: R2 ¬ R1, P: R1 ¬ R2"
    ],
    "correct": "P: R2 ¬ R1 (not confirms)"
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "The instruction ---------------will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+56]",
    "options": ["Add R3, 56", "lar R3, 56", "ldr R3, 56", "str R3, 56"],
    "correct": "ldr R3, 56"
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "----------are faster than cache memory",
    "options": ["Accumulator register", "CPU registers", "I/O devices", "ROM"],
    "correct": "CPU registers"
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "P: R3 ¬ R5 MAR ¬ IR These two are instructions written using RTL .If these two operations is to occur simultaneously then which symbol will we use to separate them so that it becomes a correct statement with the condition that two operations occur simultaneously?",
    "options": ["Arrow ¬", "Colon :", "Comma ,", "Parentheses ()"],
    "correct": "Comma ,"
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "Prefetching can be considered a primitive form of-------------",
    "options": [
      "Pipelining",
      "Multi-processing",
      "Self-execution",
      "Exception"
    ],
    "correct": "Pipelining"
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "The processor must have a way of saving information about its state or context so that it can be restored upon return from the -------------",
    "options": ["Exception", "Function", "Stack", "Thread"],
    "correct": "Exception"
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "Which one of the following circuit design levels is called the gate level?",
    "options": [
      "Logic Design Level",
      "Circuit Level",
      "Mask Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Logic Design Level"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "__________ enable the input to the PC for receiving a value that is currently on the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["LPC", "INC4", "LC", "Cout"],
    "correct": "LPC"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "________ operation is required to change the processor’s state to a known, defined value.",
    "options": ["Change", "Reset", "Update", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "Reset"
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "There are _________ types of reset operations in SRC",
    "options": ["Two", "Three", "Four", "Five"],
    "correct": "Two"
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "_____________ controller controls the sequence of the flow of microinstructions.",
    "options": ["Multiplexer", "Microprogram", "ALU", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "Microprogram"
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "FALCON-A processor bus has 16 lines or is 16-bits wide while that of SRC is __________ wide.",
    "options": ["8-bits", "24-bits", "32-bits", "64-bits"],
    "correct": "32-bits"
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "Which of the following statement(s) is/are correct about Reduced Instruction Set Computer (RISC) architectures. (i) The typical RISC machine instruction set is small, and is usually a subject of a CISC instruction set. (ii) No arithmetic or logical instruction can refer to the memory directly. (iii) A comparatively large number of user registers are available. (iv) Instructions can be easily decoded through hard-wired control units.",
    "options": [
      "(i) and (iii) only",
      "(i), (iii) and (iv)",
      "(i), (ii) and (iii) only",
      "(i),(ii),(iii) and (iv)"
    ],
    "correct": "(i),(ii),(iii) and (iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "Which one of the following register holds the instruction that is being executed?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Instruction Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "_____________all memory systems are dumb, in that they respond to only two commands: read or write",
    "options": ["Virtually", "Logically", "Physically", "None of These"],
    "correct": "Virtually"
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "To access an operand in memory, the CPU must first generate an address, which it then issues to the __________",
    "options": ["MEMORY", "REGISTER", "DATA BUS", "ALL OF ABOVE"],
    "correct": "MEMORY"
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "___________ or Branch instructions affect the order in which instructions are performed, or control the flow of the program",
    "options": ["Control", "DATA MOVMENT", "Arithmetic", "LOGICAL"],
    "correct": "Control"
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "The code size of 2-address instruction is ________________.",
    "options": ["5 bytes", "7 bytes", "3 bytes", "2 bytes"],
    "correct": "7 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "question": "The data movement instructions ___________ data within the machine and to or from input/output devices.",
    "options": ["Store", "Load", "Move", "None of Above"],
    "correct": "Move"
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "question": "Register-register instructions use ____________ memory operands out of a total of 3 operands",
    "options": ["1", "3", "0", "2"],
    "correct": "0"
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "question": "_____________all memory systems are dumb, in that they respond to only two commands: read or write.",
    "options": ["Virtually", "Logically", "Physically", "None of Above"],
    "correct": "Virtually"
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "question": "Flip-flop is a ____________device, capable of storing one bit of Information",
    "options": ["Bi-stable", "Unit-stable", "Stable", "Storage"],
    "correct": "Bi-stable"
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "question": "In which one of the following addressing modes, the value to be stored in memory is obtained by directly retrieving it from another memory location?",
    "options": [
      "Direct Addressing Mode",
      "Immediate addressing mode",
      "Indirect Addressing Mode",
      "Register (Direct) Addressing Mode"
    ],
    "correct": "Direct Addressing Mode"
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "question": "Execution time of a program with respect to the processor is calculated as:",
    "options": [
      "Execution Time = IC x CPI x MIPS",
      "Execution Time = IC x CPI x T",
      "Execution Time = CPI x T x MFLOPS",
      "Execution Time = IC x T"
    ],
    "correct": "Execution Time = IC x CPI x T"
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "question": "An “assembler” that runs on one processor and translates an assembly language program written for another processor into the machine language of the other processor is called a ----------------",
    "options": ["compiler", "cross assembler", "debugger", "linker"],
    "correct": "cross assembler"
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "question": "What functionality is performed by the instruction “lar R3, 36” of SRC?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+36]",
      "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+36).",
      "It will store the register R3 contents to the memory location M [PC+36]",
      "No operation"
    ],
    "correct": "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+36)."
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "question": "Which operator is used to „name‟ registers, or part of registers, in the Register Transfer Language?",
    "options": [":=", "&", "%", "©"],
    "correct": ":="
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "question": "What is the working of Processor Status Word (PSW)?",
    "options": [
      "To hold the current status of the processor.",
      "To hold the address of the current process",
      "To hold the instruction that the computer is currently processing",
      "To hold the address of the next instruction in memory that is to be executed"
    ],
    "correct": "To hold the current status of the processor."
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "question": "Almost every commercial computer has its own particular ---------- language",
    "options": [
      "3GL",
      "English language",
      "Higher level language",
      "assembly language"
    ],
    "correct": "assembly language"
  },
  {
    "id": 46,
    "question": "In which of the following instructions the data move between a register in the processor and a memory location (or another register) and are also called data movement?",
    "options": [
      "Arithmetic/logic",
      "Load/store",
      "Test/branch",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Load/store"
  },
  {
    "id": 47,
    "question": "What functionality is performed by the instruction “str R8, 34” of SRC?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R8 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+34]",
      "It will load the register R8 with the relative address itself (PC+34).",
      "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M [PC+34]",
      "No operation"
    ],
    "correct": "It will store the register R8 contents to the memory location M [PC+34]"
  },
  {
    "id": 48,
    "question": "What does the instruction “ldr R3, 58” of SRC do?",
    "options": [
      "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+58]",
      "It will load the register R3 with the relative address itself (PC+58).",
      "It will store the register R3 contents to the memory location M [PC+58]",
      "No operation"
    ],
    "correct": "It will load the register R3 with the contents of the memory location M [PC+58]"
  },
  {
    "id": 49,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the highest level of abstraction in digital design in which the computer architect views the system for the description of system components and their interconnections?",
    "options": [
      "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)",
      "Instruction Set Level",
      "Register Transfer Level",
      "None of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Processor-Memory-Switch level (PMS level)"
  },
  {
    "id": 50,
    "question": "Which of the instruction is used to load register from memory using a relative address?",
    "options": [
      "ld instruction",
      "ldr instruction",
      "lar instruction",
      "str instruction"
    ],
    "correct": "ldr instruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 51,
    "question": "For the __________ type instructions, we require a register to hold the data that is to be loaded from the memory, or stored back to the memory",
    "options": ["Jump", "Control", "load/store", "None of the given"],
    "correct": "load/store"
  },
  {
    "id": 52,
    "question": "The CPU includes three types of instructions, which have different operands and will need different representations. Which one of the instructions requires two source registers?",
    "options": [
      "Jump and branch format instructions",
      "Immediate format instructions",
      "Register format instructions"
    ],
    "correct": "Register format instructions"
  },
  {
    "id": 53,
    "question": "What is the size of the memory space that is available to FALCON-A processor?",
    "options": ["2^8 bytes", "2^16 bytes", "2^32 bytes", "2^64 bytes"],
    "correct": "2^16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 54,
    "question": "How can we refer to an instruction register (IR), of 16 bits (numbered 0 to 15) using RTL?",
    "options": ["IR<16..0>", "IR<15..0>", "IR<16..1>", "IR<15..1>"],
    "correct": "IR<15..0>"
  },
  {
    "id": 55,
    "question": "Which one of the following portions of an instruction represents the operation to be performed?",
    "options": ["Address", "Instruction code", "Opcode", "Operand"],
    "correct": "Opcode"
  },
  {
    "id": 56,
    "question": "Identify the opcode, destination register (DR), source registers (SA and SB i/e source register A and source register B) from the following example. ADD R1, R2, R3",
    "options": [
      "Opcode= R1, DR=ADD, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= R2, DR=ADD, SA=R1, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R3, SA=R2, SB=R1"
    ],
    "correct": "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3"
  },
  {
    "id": 57,
    "question": "What does the word „D‟ in the „D-flip-Flop‟ stands for?",
    "options": ["Data", "Digital", "Dynamic", "Double"],
    "correct": "Data"
  },
  {
    "id": 58,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the code size and the Number of memory bytes respectively for a 2-address instruction?",
    "options": [
      "4 bytes, 7 bytes",
      "7 bytes, 16 bytes",
      "10 bytes, 19 bytes",
      "13 bytes, 22 bytes"
    ],
    "correct": "7 bytes, 16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 59,
    "question": "Which of the following can be defined as an address of the operand in a computer type instruction or the target address in a branch type instruction?",
    "options": [
      "Base address",
      "Binary address",
      "Effective address",
      "All of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Effective address"
  },
  {
    "id": 60,
    "question": "Whic of the following statements is/are true about RISC processors‟ claimed advantages over CISC processors? (a) Keeping regularly accessed variables in registers as opposed to keeping them in memory facilitates faster execution. (b) RISC CPUs outperform CISC CPU‟s in procedural programming environments. (c) Instruction pipelining has helped RISC CPU‟s to attain a target of 1 cycle per instruction. (d) It is easier to maintain the “family concept” in RISC CPUs.",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b) &(c)",
      "(b), (c) & (e)",
      "(c), (d) & (e)",
      "(a), (c) & (d)"
    ],
    "correct": "(a), (c) & (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": 61,
    "question": "Which one of the following is/are the features of Register Transfer Language? a) It is a symbolic language b) It is describing the internal organization of digital computers c) It is an elementary operation performed (during one clock pulse), on the information stored in one or more registers d) It is high level language",
    "options": [
      "(b) only",
      "(a) & (b) only",
      "(a) ,(b) & (d)",
      "(b),(c) & (d)"
    ],
    "correct": "(b),(c) & (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": 62,
    "question": "Motorola MC68000 is an example of ---------microprocessor.",
    "options": ["CISC", "RISC", "SRC", "FALCON"],
    "correct": "CISC"
  },
  {
    "id": 63,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers holds the instruction that is being executed?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Instruction Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 64,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a ________ data bus.",
    "options": ["8-bit", "16-bit", "24-bit", "32-bit"],
    "correct": "16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 65,
    "question": "In which one of the following techniques, the time a processor spends waiting for instructions to be fetched from memory is minimized?",
    "options": ["Perfecting", "Pipelining", "Superscalar operation", "Speedup"],
    "correct": "Perfecting"
  },
  {
    "id": 66,
    "question": "-----------is the ability of application software to operate on models of equipment newer than the model for which it was originally developed.",
    "options": [
      "Backward compatibility",
      "Data migration",
      "Reverse engineering",
      "Upward compatibility"
    ],
    "correct": "Upward compatibility"
  },
  {
    "id": 67,
    "question": "_________ control signal allows the contents of the Program Counter register to be written onto the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["INC4", "LPC", "PCout", "LC"],
    "correct": "PCout"
  },
  {
    "id": 68,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers stores a previously calculated value or a value loaded from the main memory?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Accumulator"
  },
  {
    "id": 69,
    "question": "Computer system performance is usually measured by the ---------------",
    "options": [
      "Time to execute a program or program mix",
      "The speed with which it executes programs",
      "Processor’s utilization in solving the problems",
      "Instructions that can be carried out simultaneously"
    ],
    "correct": "Time to execute a program or program mix"
  },
  {
    "id": 70,
    "question": "Which one of the following register(s) that is/are programmer invisible and is/are required to hold an operand or result value while the bus is busy transmitting some other value?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction Register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory Buffer Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 71,
    "question": "-------------- performs the data operations as commanded by the program instructions.",
    "options": ["Control", "Data path", "Structural RTL", "Timing"],
    "correct": "Data path"
  },
  {
    "id": 72,
    "question": "Which one of the following register(s) contain(s) the address of the place the CPU wants to work with in the main memory and is/are directly connected to the RAM chips on the motherboard?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction Register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory address register"
  },
  {
    "id": 53,
    "question": "What is the size of the memory space that is available to FALCON-A processor?",
    "options": ["2^8 bytes", "2^16 bytes", "2^32 bytes", "2^64 bytes"],
    "correct": "2^16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 54,
    "question": "How can we refer to an instruction register (IR), of 16 bits (numbered 0 to 15) using RTL?",
    "options": ["IR<16..0>", "IR<15..0>", "IR<16..1>", "IR<15..1>"],
    "correct": "IR<15..0>"
  },
  {
    "id": 55,
    "question": "Which one of the following portions of an instruction represents the operation to be performed?",
    "options": ["Address", "Instruction code", "Opcode", "Operand"],
    "correct": "Opcode"
  },
  {
    "id": 56,
    "question": "Identify the opcode, destination register (DR), source registers (SA and SB i/e source register A and source register B) from the following example. ADD R1, R2, R3",
    "options": [
      "Opcode= R1, DR=ADD, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= R2, DR=ADD, SA=R1, SB=R3",
      "Opcode= ADD, DR=R3, SA=R2, SB=R1"
    ],
    "correct": "Opcode= ADD, DR=R1, SA=R2, SB=R3"
  },
  {
    "id": 57,
    "question": "What does the word „D‟ in the „D-flip-Flop‟ stands for?",
    "options": ["Data", "Digital", "Dynamic", "Double"],
    "correct": "Data"
  },
  {
    "id": 58,
    "question": "Which one of the following is the code size and the Number of memory bytes respectively for a 2-address instruction?",
    "options": [
      "4 bytes, 7 bytes",
      "7 bytes, 16 bytes",
      "10 bytes, 19 bytes",
      "13 bytes, 22 bytes"
    ],
    "correct": "7 bytes, 16 bytes"
  },
  {
    "id": 59,
    "question": "Which of the following can be defined as an address of the operand in a computer type instruction or the target address in a branch type instruction?",
    "options": [
      "Base address",
      "Binary address",
      "Effective address",
      "All of the given"
    ],
    "correct": "Effective address"
  },
  {
    "id": 60,
    "question": "Whic of the following statements is/are true about RISC processors‟ claimed advantages over CISC processors? (a) Keeping regularly accessed variables in registers as opposed to keeping them in memory facilitates faster execution. (b) RISC CPUs outperform CISC CPU‟s in procedural programming environments. (c) Instruction pipelining has helped RISC CPU‟s to attain a target of 1 cycle per instruction. (d) It is easier to maintain the “family concept” in RISC CPUs.",
    "options": [
      "(a), (b) &(c)",
      "(b), (c) & (e)",
      "(c), (d) & (e)",
      "(a), (c) & (d)"
    ],
    "correct": "(a), (c) & (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": 61,
    "question": "Which one of the following is/are the features of Register Transfer Language? a) It is a symbolic language b) It is describing the internal organization of digital computers c) It is an elementary operation performed (during one clock pulse), on the information stored in one or more registers d) It is high level language",
    "options": [
      "(b) only",
      "(a) & (b) only",
      "(a) ,(b) & (d)",
      "(b),(c) & (d)"
    ],
    "correct": "(b),(c) & (d)"
  },
  {
    "id": 62,
    "question": "Motorola MC68000 is an example of ---------microprocessor.",
    "options": ["CISC", "RISC", "SRC", "FALCON"],
    "correct": "CISC"
  },
  {
    "id": 63,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers holds the instruction that is being executed?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Instruction Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 64,
    "question": "The external interface of FALCON-A consists of a ________ data bus.",
    "options": ["8-bit", "16-bit", "24-bit", "32-bit"],
    "correct": "16-bit"
  },
  {
    "id": 65,
    "question": "In which one of the following techniques, the time a processor spends waiting for instructions to be fetched from memory is minimized?",
    "options": ["Perfecting", "Pipelining", "Superscalar operation", "Speedup"],
    "correct": "Perfecting"
  },
  {
    "id": 66,
    "question": "-----------is the ability of application software to operate on models of equipment newer than the model for which it was originally developed.",
    "options": [
      "Backward compatibility",
      "Data migration",
      "Reverse engineering",
      "Upward compatibility"
    ],
    "correct": "Upward compatibility"
  },
  {
    "id": 67,
    "question": "_________ control signal allows the contents of the Program Counter register to be written onto the internal processor bus.",
    "options": ["INC4", "LPC", "PCout", "LC"],
    "correct": "PCout"
  },
  {
    "id": 68,
    "question": "Which one of the following registers stores a previously calculated value or a value loaded from the main memory?",
    "options": [
      "Accumulator",
      "Address Mask",
      "Instruction Register",
      "Program Counter"
    ],
    "correct": "Accumulator"
  },
  {
    "id": 69,
    "question": "Computer system performance is usually measured by the ---------------",
    "options": [
      "Time to execute a program or program mix",
      "The speed with which it executes programs",
      "Processor’s utilization in solving the problems",
      "Instructions that can be carried out simultaneously"
    ],
    "correct": "Time to execute a program or program mix"
  },
  {
    "id": 70,
    "question": "Which one of the following register(s) that is/are programmer invisible and is/are required to hold an operand or result value while the bus is busy transmitting some other value?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction Register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory Buffer Register"
  },
  {
    "id": 71,
    "question": "-------------- performs the data operations as commanded by the program instructions.",
    "options": ["Control", "Data path", "Structural RTL", "Timing"],
    "correct": "Data path"
  },
  {
    "id": 72,
    "question": "Which one of the following register(s) contain(s) the address of the place the CPU wants to work with in the main memory and is/are directly connected to the RAM chips on the motherboard?",
    "options": [
      "Instruction Register",
      "Memory address register",
      "Memory Buffer Register",
      "Registers A and C"
    ],
    "correct": "Memory address register"
  }
]
